<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The corrector corrected: or, some sober reflections on a late book of Mr. Thomas Danson's published by him (as he pretends) to correct an immodest and false account (as he calls it) of two conferences between him and Mr. Ives, formerly printed about the saints perseverance. By which the former accounts of the said disputations are justified, and Mr. Danson's latter account justly blamed, as being filled with impertinencies, railings, false accusations, unchristian and unmanly reflections upon the person, opinion, and trade of his antagonist. Evidenced to the judgment of every ingenious reader. By Jer. Ives.</title>
            <author>Ives, Jeremiah, fl. 1653-1674.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1672</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 47 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 17 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A45824</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing I1097</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R221622</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99832916</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99832916</idno>
            <idno type="VID">37391</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A45824)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 37391)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2187:22)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The corrector corrected: or, some sober reflections on a late book of Mr. Thomas Danson's published by him (as he pretends) to correct an immodest and false account (as he calls it) of two conferences between him and Mr. Ives, formerly printed about the saints perseverance. By which the former accounts of the said disputations are justified, and Mr. Danson's latter account justly blamed, as being filled with impertinencies, railings, false accusations, unchristian and unmanly reflections upon the person, opinion, and trade of his antagonist. Evidenced to the judgment of every ingenious reader. By Jer. Ives.</title>
                  <author>Ives, Jeremiah, fl. 1653-1674.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 30 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>printed 1672.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>In response to Danson, Thomas.  Klētoi tetērēmēnoi, or, The Saints perseverance asserted in its positive grounds and vindicated from all material exceptions against it.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Congregational Library, London.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Danson, Thomas, d. 1694. --  Klētoi tetērēmēnoi --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Rekeyed and resubmitted</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>Taryn Hakala</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>Taryn Hakala</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:37391:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE Corrector Corrected: Or, ſome Sober REFLECTIONS On a late BOOK of Mr. <hi>THOMAS DANSON</hi>'s, Publiſhed by him (as he pretends) to Correct an immodeſt and falſe Account (as he calls it) of two Conferences between him and Mr. <hi>Ives,</hi> formerly Printed about the Saints Perſeverance.</p>
            <p>By which the former Accounts of the ſaid Diſputations are Juſtified, And Mr. <hi>Danſon</hi>'s latter Account juſtly bla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, as being filled with Impertinencies, Rail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, falſe Accuſations, unchriſtian and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manly Reflections upon the Perſon, Opinion, and Trade of his Antagoniſt.</p>
            <p>Evidenced to the Judgment of every Ingenious Reader.</p>
            <p>By <hi>Jer. Ives.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Job 11.3</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Should thy lyes make men hold their peace? And when thou mockeſt, ſhall no man make thee aſhamed?</p>
            </q>
            <p>Contemptum ſtulti contemnere maxima laus eſt; Contemni à ſtulto dedecus eſſe nego.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed 1672.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:37391:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:37391:2"/>
            <head>THE Corrector Corrected, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>IT hath alway been, and ſtill is the Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod of the adverſaries to Truth, to make Calumnies and Falſhood, the greateſt part of their offenſive Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour; having learned that old Greek advice, <hi>That to Calumniate ſtoutly, for that how perfectly the wound of reproch be healed, there will remain a ſcar; and though we wipe away with never ſo much care the dirt thrown at us, ſome ſullage will be left behinde:</hi> Accordingly this was the Expedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent the Pagans uſed againſt the Primitive Chriſtians, to put them in the Skins of Beaſts, and ſhapes of Monſters, and then worry them to death. Had this been only the ſtratagem of Heathens, the wonder had long ſince ceaſed: But alas! theſe Unchri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Weapons have been too much uſed in Chriſtian Warfare; as if Chriſtianity could not ſubſiſt without a Heatheniſh Auxiliary,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:37391:3"/>It is ſad to obſerve theſe Pagan Copies, ſo often tranſcribed by Chriſtian Combatants, who though they pretend to advance Truth, yet make Calumny and Falſhood their Inſtruments. Now that theſe have been the chief Weapons of Mr. <hi>Danſon</hi>'s Warfare, together with his idle and bald Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>militudes, his Illogical Arguing, his giving the go-by to that he could not anſwer, his notorious falſifying of what was both ſaid and Printed; with which not only his diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puting, but his late Book abounds withall; the evincing whereof is the ground of this preſent Undertaking.</p>
            <p>I ſhall begin with his Calumniating, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with he begins his Book, telling the Reader in the very beginning of his Epiſtle, <hi>That I am guilty of ſuch Immorality in Converſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, that they are aſhamed of me that do a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree with me in Opinion; again, that I am guilty of deteſtable Arrianiſme, and denying the Godhead of Chriſt, and that I have never repented of it as he knows of; and therefore all Chriſtians by Profeſſion have cauſe to be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhamed of me,</hi> &amp;c. Upon the whole of this Charge, I ſhall make theſe modeſt De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands.</p>
            <p>Firſt, What Mr. <hi>Danſon</hi> means by Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morality? For if by Immorality he means a coming ſhort of the ſtrictneſs of the Moral
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:37391:3"/>Law, which is to love God with all my heart, and my neighbour as my ſelf, I muſt with the reſt of mankind plead guilty; and if this be Mr. <hi>Danſon</hi>'s meaning, he ſhould not have thrown the firſt ſtone till himſelf had been without ſin: But if by Immorality he means ſome capital and notorious Crimes, (for that ſeems to be his meaning, becauſe he ſaith they are ſuch, for which <hi>thoſe are aſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med of me that agree with me in Opinion</hi>) I here upon demand.</p>
            <p>Secondly, Whether Mr. <hi>Danſon</hi> chargeth me with Immorality upon his own know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, or upon hear-ſay and report? If upon his own knowledge, why did he not uſe means to reclaim me before he did publickly defame me? and inſtance the particular Acts wherein I was thus guilty, together with the names of his Evidences: If Mr. <hi>Danſon</hi> had this ſtory of my Immorality but upon report, I demand whether it is not groſs Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morality, contrary to the Law of God and Nature, not only to take up, but to Print a report or reproch againſt ones neighbour? It's contrary to the Law of Nature, becauſe Mr. <hi>Danſon</hi> would not be ſo ſerved himſelf; contrary to the written Law of God, <hi>Levit.</hi> 19.16. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 15.3. <hi>Jer.</hi> 20.10. <hi>Ezek.</hi> 22.9. which expreſly forbids taking up reports a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt our neighbour.</p>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:37391:4"/>
            <p>Thirdly, I demand whether Mr. <hi>Danſon</hi> thinks <hi>George Whitehead</hi> did well to report, and Print in his Book of the Divinity of Chriſt, <hi>Page</hi> 49. that he was given to game<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, Bowls, and Nine-pins, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Yet how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever <hi>George</hi> was more ingenious; becauſe he inſtances the particulars of his Charge, and not like Mr. <hi>Danſon,</hi> to traduce in ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral terms, and inſtance in no particulars. Now if this was ill done in him, thus to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port of Mr. <hi>Danſon,</hi> ſurely it cannot be well done of Mr. <hi>Danſon,</hi> thus to take up and Print Reports againſt me.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, Whereas Mr. <hi>Danſon</hi> ſaith, that ſuch is my Immortality, that they are aſhamed of me that agree with me in opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; I demand how that can be, when I have converſed this 30. years among thoſe of my own opinion, and with whom I ſtill have my converſation through the Grace of God, whom I dare appeal to in this mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and who were the men, as Mr. <hi>Danſon</hi> confeſſeth in the 2 <hi>Page</hi> of his Epiſtle, that did ſubſtitute me to diſpute with him, though he ſaith they are aſhamed of me.</p>
            <p>As to the ſecond part of this charge, <hi>that I am a deteſtable Arrian, and deny the God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head of Chriſt, for which all Chriſtians ſhould be aſhamed of me;</hi> this becauſe it is a particular inſtance, requires a particular
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:37391:4"/>Anſwer: I therefore deny that ever I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied the Godhead of Chriſt; I did never by Word or Writing aſſert any ſuch thing, but the contrary. and I challenge any man to prove it either from my Words or Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings; for there is no other way of proof that I know of, and to put the matter fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther out of doubt, and rowl away this re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proch. I do profeſs before God, Angels and Men, that I do believe Jeſus Chriſt to be God bleſſed for ever, Amen, according to <hi>Rom.</hi> 9.5. not only my Lord, but my God, <hi>John</hi> 20.28. And to the truth of this I appeal to all Chriſtians that know me, whether I have not, and do not give Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Honour and Adoration to Jeſus Chriſt the Son of God, of whom the Author to the <hi>Hebrews</hi> thus ſpeaks, and which I do firmly believe, <hi>Heb.</hi> 1.8. <hi>But unto the Son he ſaith, thy Throne O God is for ever and ever:</hi> Whence it is not only men, but even all the Angels of God are required to Worſhip him, <hi>Ver.</hi> 6.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, upon the whole of this charge I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand, whether he that publiſhes, or reports any one for ſcandalous and blaſphemous, (for ſuch is imorality and denying the Godhead of Chriſt) and doth not publiſh his Evidence, ought not juſtly to be ſuſpect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to be the Author of thoſe reports, and the Inventor of thoſe evil things.</p>
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:37391:5"/>
            <p>After he hath done with this, he begins to beat me with barbariſm, telling me that <hi>I out-faced him,</hi> Epiſt. Page 3. <hi>That I was more bold then wiſe;</hi> becauſe I ſent to him to deſire him to appoint time and place to view the Copy of the diſputes before I Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted them, <hi>Epiſt. Page</hi> 4. Again in <hi>Page</hi> 49. he ſaith, <hi>I make no Conſcience of lying to ſlu my Adverſary, and that I was rude and clamerous,</hi> and that he <hi>could not be heard for my rudeneſs,</hi> Page 40. 50. He reflects upon my Trade, <hi>Page</hi> 8. calls <hi>me impudence in the height,</hi> Page 58. Tells me <hi>I have a brow of Braſs,</hi> Page 84. So in the diſpute he <hi>called me ignorant, diſingenious, impudent fellow,</hi> ſee my Book <hi>Page</hi> 156. 158. and in <hi>Page</hi> 41. of his Book, he calls me <hi>igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>and diſingenious,</hi> upon the whole I demand of any man that hath not polluted his credit &amp; his Conſcience to, whether ſuch words of this Preacher are ever like to Adminiſter Grace to either hearers or readers? 2 where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as he charges me with rude and uncivil be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haviour in general terms; I demand whether he hath inſtanced in all his Book of any one hard word, rude or uncivil expreſſion that fell from my lips in the diſputations, or from my Pen in the publiſhing of them, though often provoked by his ill language. I chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenge envy it ſelf to give me an inſtance
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:37391:5"/>and yet this man complains of my rudeneſs, and in his Epiſtle Page 2, confidently tells his Reader, <hi>that thoſe that were abſent knew how I demean'd myſelf as perfectly as they that were preſent:</hi> Surely he thinks all that know me have a Spirit of Divination, elſe they could never know my behaviour, <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s <hi>PERFECT<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>LY</hi> in their abſence, as if they were preſent with me, and to make me amends; for all this he tells his Reader in his Epiſt e Page 6. that he forbears to inlarge; <hi>becauſe it would but give tht world a ſight of rudeneſs and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertenency in their natural deformity.</hi> Now the man think I muſt thank him for his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour, but I ſhall only ſay, <hi>ſtul orum gratia in grata.</hi> He complains Page 65. that <hi>he could not be heard for my Stentorian voice,</hi> a hard word, which he found in ſome of his Boys Dictionaries, taken from a <hi>Gracian,</hi> whoſe name was <hi>Stentor,</hi> who with his voice, it's ſaid, would make a greater noiſe then 50. men together, ſuch a voice I have, if you will believe Mr. <hi>Danſon,</hi> thus this mans Tongue doth traduce by inſtinct, and is ſo venomous that it cannot touch unleſs it ſting, and his Pen drops a train of ſly and malicious words, and that (he thinks) is enough to blow up any ones reputation by this Art (as one well obſerves) <hi>Men are wounded with doubtful intimations, and ſtab'd with an ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:37391:6"/>like look, it is but raiſing ſuſpicions, and an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>different Logitian will find out the Catagorical meanings of thoſe oblique reprochings,</hi> and as if ſlanders lay point blank with the level of his Genus he begins to ſow this Seed in the mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of his Book, and in the evening of it this hand doth not reſt; he ſaith in the cloſe of his Book, <hi>That there is not a ruder ſort of people (the quakers not excepted) then the</hi> Arminian <hi>Anabaptiſts, &amp; this he ſays is the common opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion that ſober perſons have of them,</hi> thus you ſee that one perſon is too mean a prey for his great Spirit to quarry upon, a whole party is little enough to fall by his fatal blows, thus as with the Jaw bone of an Aſs heaps upon heaps we fall by thouſands, I ſhall cloſe this with a ſober ſaying of Dr. <hi>Sibs</hi> upon the <hi>Canticles</hi> Page 285. <hi>This (ſaith he) is a thing that ſprings from the poiſonous pride of mens hearts, that when they cannot raiſe themſelves by their own worth they will en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour to do it by the ruining anothers credit.</hi> Thus Mr. <hi>Crandon,</hi> Mr. <hi>Eyres,</hi> Mr. <hi>Bagſhaw,</hi> deals with Mr. <hi>Baxter,</hi> the former by ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemnly accuſing him in print for a <hi>Papiſt,</hi> and the ſecond by charging him alſo in Print, that when he writ againſt <hi>Antino<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mians,</hi> that he meant <hi>Antipapiſts,</hi> and that he was a <hi>Socinian, and a Papiſt, and a Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuit,</hi> ſo confeſſion of Faith, Page 6. the
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:37391:6"/>latter, <hi>viz.</hi> Mr. <hi>Bagſhaw</hi> accuſeth him for <hi>one of the worſt ſort of Hereticks; Bagſhaw</hi> Defence of the Antidote, in his Advertiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment at the latter end of the Book: And this way the <hi>Jeſuits</hi> went to defame <hi>Luther</hi> and <hi>Calvin,</hi> by ſpreading it abroad, <hi>that they denied the Majeſty of God, and the Dei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of Chriſt.</hi> This way Mr. <hi>Edwards</hi> in his <hi>Gangrena</hi> took to beſpatter all perſons whoſe Opinions he could not confute; and this way Mr. <hi>Danſon</hi> takes to beſpatter me, as if his deſign were more to blaſt his Adverſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries Fame, then to confute his Errours; and for the better effecting of it, his Book a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bounds with uncouth and bald Similitudes, thereby to affect the ears of the vulgar, whoſe temper is aptly ſuited to receive ill impreſſions.</p>
            <p>In page 57. of his Book, when he could not reply to the force of my Anſwer, he inſtead of rejoyning, tells his Reader, that <hi>my An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer did me no more ſervice, then a Mouſe ſtruggling to get out of a Tar-barrel;</hi> and in his Epiſtle, page 2. as if he had lately been at a Cock-fighting, he ſaith, <hi>If he ſhould not have diſputed, I would have crowed like a Cock on a Dunghill;</hi> but to whom this ſimilitude is beſt applied, may eaſily be diſcerned: for when I ſent a Letter to Mr. <hi>Danſon,</hi> to tell him I could not meet at the
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:37391:7"/>time he appointed me, and to which I never agreed, yet this man ſent me word in a Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, that he would not alter the time, (though of his own appointing) but accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly met (if I may uſe his phraſe) upon his own Dunghill, <hi>viz</hi> the place of his own appointing, where he took the liberty to crow, ſufficiently knowing before that there would be none to oppoſe him. He further addes, as if he had been at a Fencing-School, that if he had not diſputed, <hi>my party would have gone away ſinging, IO TRI<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>MPHE:</hi> And in page 6. of his Epiſtle, as if he had lately been at the Bear-Garden, he comes in with his Beariſh Similitude, and tell me, <hi>That like the Bear I licked my Cubs into a better ſhape then they had at their Birth.</hi> Sure this is barharous Engliſh for a Schollar to talk of the <hi>Birth of Bears:</hi> Again, in his Epiſtle page 5. he ſaith <hi>I made him father my brats.</hi> Is not this rich Rhetorick? But his ſtock of Similitudes being all exhauſted, he goes a bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowing of a greazy one of Dr. <hi>Tho. Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>win,</hi> as himſelf confeſſeth in his Book, page 37. by which he would compare the increaſe of Grace to making of Candles; <hi>When a Candle (ſaith he) is put into a Fat of boyled Tallow, every time it is put in, it comes out bigger and bigger,</hi> &amp;c. Really it argues a man hath but a little Learning, and a very
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:37391:7"/>barren Wit that muſt go a borrowing for ſuch ſorry Similitudes: Thus you ſee he loves to diſport himſelf with Tropes, Meta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phors, and Similitudes. But to proceed, his Logick correſponds with his Rhetorick; for if it be true as he ſaith, (then which nothing is more falſe) that I did not rightly l<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y down ſome two or three of his Arguments in his own terms; and if it were true, that ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times I deny'd the <hi>major</hi> when the Syllogiſm was Hypothetical, and therefore ſhould have denyed the Conſequence rather; ſuppoſe all this that he corrects me for, were deſerved<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to be corrected, yet that which he doth not deny when I accuſe him of it, I hope that may be taken for granted, (and that his ſilence herein, according to the Proverb, may well be interpreted for conſent) and and then let the Reader but conſider how often I charged him in the Diſpute with beg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging the Queſtion, inſtead of proving it with attempting to make Arguments ſeveral times one after another, and could not for a long time conclude the Queſtion; ſee page 84. to 91. of my Book: And did not I in the Diſputation thrice appeal to his Friend Mr. <hi>Fowler,</hi> who alſo gave it againſt him? which did not ſatisfie him, but ſtill he would have argued without concluding the Queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in debate. See page 94. how often did I
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:37391:8"/>charge him with running in a Ring, and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puting circularly, and of falſe Syllogiſms, arguing <hi>idem per idem,</hi> to all which he makes no defence, but ſaith page 43. I wrong'd him by ſaying, he argued that what ever was potential hath been done; yet as if the man and his ſenſes were parted, he confeſſeth he argued, that if Believers can fall away, ſome have; and that he did argue <hi>a poſſe ad eſſe,</hi> which is in Engliſh the ſame thing; therefore I conclude, that he being conſcious of the Truth of what I charged him with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all, he thought it the beſt way to paſs it over in ſilence, as he doth thoſe Quotations out of St. <hi>Auſtin,</hi> where I ſhew beyond con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradiction, that not onely <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e, but <hi>Proſper</hi> and <hi>Fulgentius,</hi> and the Church of God for thirteen or fourteen hundred years were of my mind touching the Point in Queſtion; which he makes no reply to, though this was ſtifly denied in the Diſputation.</p>
            <p>Again, page 43. of my Book, I charge him with taking up my Interpretation of the firſt of <hi>John</hi> to confute the <hi>Quakers,</hi> when he diſcourſed with them; and with taking up the <hi>Quakers</hi> Interpretation of the ſame Text, to confute me, as any man may ſee, that compareth 42, 43, 44, 45. of my Book, with page 3, 4. &amp; 6.36. &amp; 44. of his Book called <hi>The Quakers folly,</hi> much like
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:37391:8"/>thoſe fraudulent Chapmen, that have one weight to buy by, and another to ſell by. Now he in his late Book, inſtead of anſwer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſo material an Objection tells the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der page 9. <hi>that it is ſo trivial, that it de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerves a ſmile rather then an anſwer:</hi> An eaſie way to anſwer Objections, which was a frequent humour in Mr. <hi>Danſon,</hi> and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny others of his way then preſent at the Diſputation, to fall a laughing and ſcoffing, on purpoſe to animate the people in ſo do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; ſee my Book page 114, 115. for no other reaſon, but becauſe I told them that the Seed of God, 1 <hi>John</hi> 2. might be under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood for the Word of God, according as Chriſt interprets the phraſe, <hi>Mat.</hi> 13. And though I blamed him and them in their Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putations for their Levity; yet he neither denies the Charge, nor makes any other De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence. But I underſtand that this is not the firſt time that he and his party hath been charged with it; <hi>George Whitehead</hi> in Print complaining of it, in his Account of the Diſputations between him and Mr. <hi>Danſon,</hi> though I confeſs Mr. <hi>Danſon</hi> ſaith more for himſelf in his reply to <hi>George Whitehead,</hi> then his conſcience would ſuffer him to ſay in his reply to me, <hi>viz.</hi> that he did ſpeak ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral times to ſtill the people of his Perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion when he diſputed with the <hi>Quakers;</hi>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:37391:9"/>though he would never open his lips upon that account, in his diſputing with me; though he ſaw me take ſo much pains to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treat thoſe of his party to be ſilent and civil.</p>
            <p>Likewiſe when I charge him with ſaying, he could not prove his <hi>major</hi> Propoſition, page 84. ſo great was the ſtraight he was then in, that he is not yet out of it; for elſe we ſhould have heard him ſay ſomething for himſelf in his Reply, but not a word of this.</p>
            <p>Another main thing he gives the go-by, is my charging his Doctrine with Novelty, and to ſymbolize with Antinominianiſm, to thoſe many Inſtances I bring of the Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity of the contrary Opinion, quoted by Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> out of St. <hi>Auſtin,</hi> and others, he ſaith nothing, but quotes Dr <hi>Kendall, Hier. Zanch</hi> See his Book page 80, 81 but not a word what they ſay; and ſurrher tell us, that St. <hi>Auſtin</hi> writ a Book <hi>de perſev. Sanct, and diſtinguiſheth often between com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon and ſpecial grace:</hi> But what is this to the purpoſe? Da<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>h this take off the force of what St. <hi>Auſtin</hi> ſaith about the poſſibility of true Believers falling away, (which I urged in my Book once and again, and he ſ<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ith nothing to it) and to what I alledg'd out of Mr. <hi>Baxter,</hi> he ſaith page 81. <hi>that
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:37391:9"/>worthy perſon doth not determine againſt what he holds;</hi> What a piece of impertinency is here? Do not I ſay once and again, page 173, 175. that though it was not Mr. <hi>Baxter,</hi> own perſwaſion, yet he confeſſeth it was the perſwaſion of the Church of God for thirteen or fourteen hundred years; and for this Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> quotes good Authority, which inſtead of taking off, he ſaith not a word to, onely tells his Reader what I told him before, that Mr. <hi>Baxer</hi> diſſents from me. But what is this to the purpoſe, unleſs I had charged Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> with being of my Opinion.</p>
            <p>But the Antient Churches, as well as Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dern, which I do ſay were of my mind, Mr. <hi>Danſon</hi> hath no mind to meddle with; and whereas I do charge their Doctrine to ſym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bolize with Antinomianiſm in many particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar Inſtances, too plain to be deny'd; inſtead of taking off thoſe Inſtances, he brings in Mr. <hi>Carril,</hi> to whom he ſaith he ſubſcribes, which, ſaith he, ſpeaks the ſenſe of them, (meaning of thoſe men whoſe Books I quote) ſee his Book page 81. where he quotes theſe paſſages from Mr. <hi>Carrill,</hi> on of his Comment upon theſe words, <hi>Job</hi> 10.15. <hi>If I be wicked, woe unto me,</hi> &amp;c They (ſaith he) put dangerous ſuppoſitions <hi>contrary to this, that ſay, Let a godly man be never ſo wicked, let him ſin as much as he will, yet it ſall be well with him [this ſaith Mr.</hi> Danſon
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:37391:10"/>
               <hi>is the language of ſuch as Dr.</hi> Criſp, <hi>which Mr.</hi> Ives <hi>quotes, and we diſown</hi>] and then he adds, <hi>though there be a truth in it, that how much ſoever a godly man ſinneth he ſhall be pardoned.</hi> For the unriddling this Riddle, I muſt make theſe enquiries.</p>
            <p>Firſt, Whether it be not as dangerous a ſuppoſition to ſuppoſe that if a godly man ſin never ſo much, he ſhall be pardoned, as to ſuppoſe that if a godly man be never ſo wicked, it ſhall be well with him, ſince the latter of theſe Mr. <hi>Carril</hi> and Mr. <hi>Danſon</hi> both ſay is contrary to what <hi>Job</hi> ſuppoſeth; but the former they ſay hath a truth in it.</p>
            <p>Secondly, Since Mr. <hi>Danſon</hi> ſaith, <hi>that it is the language of ſuch as Dr.</hi> Criſp <hi>to ſay, that let a godly man ſin never ſo much it ſhall be well with him, which</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>is the language which we diſown;</hi> yet withall he adds, <hi>that there is a truth in it, that how much ſoever a godly man ſins he ſhall be par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doned;</hi> whereupon I demand how Mr. <hi>Dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon</hi> can diſown it, and in the next Sentence ſay there is a truth in it?</p>
            <p>Thirdly, I demand how it can be a <hi>dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous ſuppoſition,</hi> and yet a true ſuppoſition? To ſuppoſe that if a godly man ſins never ſo much he ſhall be pardoned; for he ſaith there is a truth in it, and yet ſaith it is dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous; but what danger is there to aſſert and believe a truth, unleſs it be a danger to Mr. <hi>Danſons</hi> reputation when his people ſhall
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:37391:10"/>perceive him ſo palpably contradictious to himſelf?</p>
            <p>Fourthly, Whereas Mr. <hi>Carril</hi> and Mr. <hi>Danſon</hi> (both ſay) that there is a truth in that ſuppoſition, <hi>that how much ſoever a god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly man ſins he ſhall be pardoned;</hi> and yet in the next words tells us, <hi>that the Scripture uſeth no ſuch language.</hi> And Mr. <hi>Carril</hi> (upon the ſame place in <hi>Job</hi>) ſaith, <hi>The Spirit of God makes no ſuch ſuppoſition; and the form of wholeſome words, teacheth every man rather to ſpeak thus, if I am wicked woe unto me:</hi> Hence I demand how there can be a truth in any divine Doctrin which is not the language of holy Scripture? No marvail Mr. <hi>Danſon</hi> was angry, and called me a <hi>conceited ignorant Fellow,</hi> when I called upon him for a plain Text to prove his Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine; ſee my Book, page 156. ſince he ſaith there is a truth in this Doctrine, though (he ſaith) <hi>it be not the language of the Scripture, nor according to the form of wholeſome words.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>He that can reſolve theſe queſtions, and can reconcile ſuch palpable contradictions, ſhall be my <hi>magnus Apollo (viz.)</hi> that a Doctrine can be dangerous and contrary to what <hi>Job</hi> ſpeaks, and yet true, a ſuppoſition as the Spirit of God no where ſuppoſeth, and which is not found in the language of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Scripture, and form of wholeſome words, and yet true; and which Mr. <hi>Danſon</hi> himſelf ſaith he diſowns, and yet after all this ſaith,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:37391:11"/>there is a truth in it! When Mr. <hi>Danſon</hi> hath reconciled theſe Sentences, I will have them advanced into the number of <hi>Orthodox para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doxes.</hi> But what is all this to the matter ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected in page 104 of my book <hi>(viz.)</hi> that Mr. <hi>Danſon</hi> ſaith in his book of the <hi>Quakers folly,</hi> page 38. <hi>That</hi> David <hi>when he was guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of Murder and Adultry, was not in a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned, but a juſtified state;</hi> This though I charge him with it once and again; yet like a man afraid or aſhamed, he paſſeth by it, and ſaith nothing at all to it; and whereas I charge others of them (in divers if their books which I refer to in my Appendix) with ſaying <hi>the regenerate dye in Chriſt, though they dye in impenitency; and that the people of God need not queſtion their condition, though their ſins be never ſo great; and that God lov<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the</hi> Corinthians <hi>in their Adulteries, Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries, and ungodlyneſs, as much as when they were believers, waſhed, juſtified, and ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied. And that it is not the manner of Gods people to confeſs and forſake their ſin in order to Salvation, and that they that cannot preach mex ſins are forgiven, till they ſee them repent and reform their lives, are ignorant preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, and that no ſin any true believer can com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit, can move God to hate them, neither will God love them ever a whit the worſe, though they commit never ſo many and ſo great ſins;</hi> Theſe are the Antinomian notions I charge Mr. <hi>Danſon</hi> and divers of his Brethren with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:37391:11"/>of which charge he in his book promiſed to clear them. See his Epiſtle to his book, page 6. But I think they will never give him thanks for his labour, when they ſhall find that he takes no notice of all theſe pernicious doctrines, aſſerted by them, and charged up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them, as any one may ſee that reads his book; but inſtead of clearing them, brings Mr. <hi>Carril</hi> to ſpeak the ſame thing for them all, by which he confirms the whole charge, <hi>(viz.) that if a godly man ſins never ſo much, it ſhall be forgiven him, though the Scripture</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>uſeth no ſuch language.</hi> But if this godly man have not ſinned himſelf out of his ſenſes, he will never believe ſuch Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters that tell them of pardons that are not to be found in the Scriptures, nor ſuppoſed by the ſpirit of God, as Mr. <hi>Carril</hi> and Mr. <hi>Danſon</hi> confeſſeth; ſee Mr. <hi>Carril</hi> upon <hi>Job</hi> 10.16. and Mr. <hi>Danſon</hi> ſubſcribing to him in his book page 81.. Sure I am a little tick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>et from <hi>Rome</hi> (as one calls it) will as ſoon aſſure a godly man of pardon, though he ſins never ſo much (as Mr. <hi>Danſon</hi> can aſſure him in the like caſe, if ſuch doctrines are not the language of holy Scripture) For would not this be a wonderful Cordial to a godly man in an hour of deſertion and temptation, to tell him that he need not be caſt down; for though he hath ſinned never ſo much againſt God he ſhall be pardoned; and to aſſure him of the truth of this comfortable Doctrine,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:37391:12"/>tell him Mr. <hi>Danſon</hi> ſaith, and Mr. <hi>Carril</hi> ſaith, <hi>there is a truth in it, though it be not the language of holy Scripture.</hi> Were it not much better for this godly man to ſend for a Romiſh Prieſt, and take abſolution from him; for in ſo doing he ſhall have the Faith of their Church for his aſſurance, though he hath no word of God for it, and I think that as good, if not better, then the aſſurance of ſuch par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dons Mr. <hi>Danſon</hi> talks of, which he ſaith are not found in the language of holy Scripture.</p>
            <p>Other antinomian paſſages he hath, p. 32. 33. which like the Papiſts he accounts for truth, though they are not found in the lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage of the holy Scripture, <hi>(viz.)</hi> that <hi>David</hi> in his committing Murder, and Adul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, did never wickedly depart from God, and to prove this, he ſuborns the <hi>18th. Pſalm</hi> for a witneſs, where <hi>David</hi> ſays, <hi>I have not wick<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>edly departed from God:</hi> whence he infers, that <hi>David</hi> never wickedly departed fron him. but whoever conſiders 2 <hi>Sam</hi> 22. ſhall find that <hi>David</hi> likewiſe faith, <hi>that he did not depart from Gods ſtatutes,</hi> and <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119. <hi>v.</hi> 101, 102. <hi>I have</hi> (ſaith David) <hi>refrained my feet from every evil way, and I have not departed from thy judgments.</hi> May not a man as well argue that <hi>David</hi> never ſinned, becauſe he ſaith, <hi>I have refrained my feet from every evil way,</hi> and that he had never departed from Gods ſtatutes becauſe he ſaith, <hi>I have not departed from them,</hi> as ſay as Mr. <hi>Danſon</hi> ſaith, that becauſe <hi>David</hi>
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:37391:12"/>ſays, <hi>I have not wickedly departed from God,</hi> that therefore he never wickedly departed from him; For by the ſame parity of reaſon that <hi>David</hi> did not wickedly depart from God in the committing Murder, and Adultry; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he ſays, <hi>I have not wickedly departed from God:</hi> I ſay by the ſame reaſon he did not ſin in committing Murder, and Adultry; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the Scripture likewiſe ſays in the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cited places, that he had refrained his feet from every evil way.</p>
            <p>Again, we have more of this Antinomian Spirit moving upon the Superficies of the <hi>30th.</hi> and <hi>31ſt</hi> p. of his book, in words at length and not in figures, he ſaith, <hi>though Christ might juſtifie a divorce; yet it appears not that he will ſue out one againſt any believer that is guilty of bodily Adultry.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This is the man that tells his Reader in his Epiſtle, p. 6. <hi>that he will vindicate their do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine from the charge of Antinomianiſm, and that he diſowns the language of ſuch as Dr.</hi> Criſp, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> p 88.</p>
            <p>Now in p. 195. of my book, I quote Dr. <hi>Griſp</hi> in his Sermon of <hi>Chriſt is the way,</hi> ſaying, <hi>that if a believer be overtaken with a groſs ſin, none dare ſerve a Writ of Damnation upon him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And though Mr. <hi>Danſon</hi> would make his Reader believe, he diſowns Dr. <hi>Criſp</hi> &amp;c. yet he ſaith the ſame thing; for he ſaith, <hi>Chriſt will not ſue out a divorce againſt a believer, though guilty of bodily Adultry.</hi> Dr. <hi>Crisp</hi>
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:37391:13"/>ſaith, none can ſerve a Writ of Damnation pon them, though they are guilty of groſs ſins. Thus you may ſee how Mr. <hi>Danſon</hi> clears himſelf of Antomianiſm, and diſowns Dr. <hi>Crisps</hi> Language; juſt like him that to clear himſelf of worſhipping the ſimilitude of the Virgin <hi>Mary,</hi> and to diſown any ſuch charge ſaid, that he did not worſhip her ſimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litude; but he worſhipped her likeneſs; after this rate doth Mr. <hi>Danſon</hi> diſown Dr. <hi>Crisp,</hi> and Antinomianiſm.</p>
            <p>I now proceed to anſwer his falſe charges touching our conferences, which I doubt not but I ſhall diſcharge my ſelf of in the judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of all impartial perſons, at a better rate then Mr. <hi>Danſon</hi> hath cleared himſelf of An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tomianiſm.</p>
            <p>The two main things he charges my book, with is, omiſſions of many things that paſt in the Diſputes; and aſſerting ſome things to have been ſpoken by him, that he never ſpoke.</p>
            <p>To this I anſwer, Firſt, that I did not write out the Diſputes my ſelf; but they were writ out by a perſon that is neither Presbyterian, nor Anabaptiſt, who took both days conferen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces in Characters; and had no reaſon that I know of, to be partial; and who is ready if need be to arreſt upon Oath, that thoſe things were aſſerted by Mr. <hi>Danſon</hi> in the conferen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces which he denies in his book; among which, this is one paſſage, in page 83. of my book, <hi>(viz.) that whatever is potential hath been
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:37391:13"/>done:</hi> this Mr. <hi>Danſon</hi> in the <hi>43d</hi> p. of his book ſaith, <hi>were not his but my words.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But beſides what may be evidenced by him that writ the Diſpute, that theſe were Mr. <hi>Danſons</hi> words; I offer the conſideration of what is publiſhed in p 83, 84 of my book, where this very propoſition of Mr. <hi>Danſons,</hi> was more largely debated him, and I preſſed him to the proof of it, to that height, that he was forced to anſwer <hi>he could not prove it;</hi> as any may ſee that reads my book p. 84 and which he doth not ſo much as deny in any part of his own book.</p>
            <p>But further, to ſhew my ſincerity in this matter, and that I did no way deſign to abuſe Mr, <hi>Danſon,</hi> or he World with falcities; I writ to him to appoint me time and place when and where I might meet with him, that he might have liberty to correct the Copy, that it might be publiſhed by conſent, the Copy of which Letter is printed in my Book, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed by Mr. <hi>Danſon</hi> in the 4. Page of the Epiſtle to his Book, and for which he tells me <hi>I was mo<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e bold then wiſe.</hi> Now let all inge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nious men judge whether my thus ſending to him to come and view the Copy, and correct it if need were, did beſpeak me to be a perſon that intended to miſrepreſent him, and whether his refuſing to meet me upon ſo fair an invitation, and upon ſo juſt an occaſion; doth not rather be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpeak him too conſcious of his own folly, and therefore was unwilling to meet, leaſt he ſhould
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:37391:14"/>have been contributary to the manifeſtation of it</p>
            <p>Beſides (as Mr. <hi>Danſon</hi> deridingly tells his Reader once and again) I had all my Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments written in my Note Book, and ſo might be better capable to correct any error in the Scribe. then Mr. <hi>Danſon,</hi> who was ſo far from having Arguments in his hand, that at ſome turns he had none in his head, but ſometimes when he was right in his Premiſes, he was out in his Concluſion, and other whiles when he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded the thing denied, his Premiſes was falſe, from whence he would infer it; this I have charged him with ſeveral times, which was ſo manifeſt, that he durſt not in this matter plead not guilty in all his Book, and therefore I leave any to judge, whoſe Judgments are not fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtalled, whether (theſe Circumſtances con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered) I have added any thing to the confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rences, or imputed any thing to Mr. <hi>Danſon,</hi> but what in truth he is chargeable with.</p>
            <p>But I have an Argument yet more convin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing, to prove he chargeth me falſly; becauſe he complains that I have left out of my Book divers things to the weakening his Arguments and Anſwers, that I might render him ridi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culous. Now that man as ſhall be ſo daring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly bold as to tell his Reader once and again, that I have left that out of my Book which is plainly and expreſly in it, may be juſtly ſuſpected to ſpeak falſly in other things, and that he charges me falſly in this matter, appears,</p>
            <p>Firſt, In Page 2. of his Book, he ſaith, the
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:37391:14"/>term <hi>true believers was not in the minor propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition denied.</hi> Now whoever looks into the 2. and 3. Page of my Book ſhall ſee it is both im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied and expreſt, beſides he expreſſeth it in his own Book in his repition of the Argument, Page 2, and yet he ſaith, <hi>the term true believers was not in the minor propoſition,</hi> I ſee the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verb is true that A — muſt have a good memory; for he reports the words in his own account he gives of the diſpute, and preſently after ſaith thoſe words were not in the Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.</p>
            <p>Secondly, He ſaith Page 2 that in my ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of the conference, I left out <hi>his diſtincti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of what was impoſſible to be done, by reaſon of the Divine decree, or promiſe though other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe poſſible, [with reſpect to the nature of the thing] all this (ſaith he) Mr.</hi> Ives <hi>left out.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>When I have not only put it all in; but have added a Paraphraſe upon that diſtinction in a different Character, and that I have put in this diſtinction in my anſwers, appears in the 27 Page of my Book, where you have me ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to Mr. <hi>Danſon</hi> in theſe words. <hi>You gave this diſtinction that the command was poſſible in it ſelf, or in relation to the ſubject commanded, but not poſſible with reſpect to the decree of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And in a few lines following, I Print Mr. <hi>Danſon</hi> repling in theſe words. <hi>I ſaid that thoſe Cautions that are given to viſible believers in ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral, that they ſhould take heed of falling away,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:37391:15"/>did ſuppoſe the poſſibility of it in the nature of the thing (in true believers alſo) becauſe man is but mutable, and Grace is but a Creature, and therefore certainly may be loſt, and yet it is certainly impoſſible as to true believers upon the ſuppoſition of the Divine decree, and Chriſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe to preſence and uphold the Grace of true be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lievers,</hi> to which I ſubjoyn in a different Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter as a further Anſwer upon his diſtinction, <hi>this is juſt as if a man ſhould ſay the whole earth is poſſible to be overflowed with Water, with re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spect to the Nature of the thing, though with reſpect to the decree of God it is impoſſible, but then I add, that if God hath made ſuch a decree, no man hath any more reaſon to fear a univerſal inundation, becauſe of ſuch a decree, then he had to fear it if it were impoſſible, with reſpect to the nature of the thing, in like manner if it be im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible to fall from Grace with reſpect to the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cree of God, there is no more reaſon to fear fall<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing then there would have been, had it been im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible with reſpect to the nature of the thing.</hi> Thus I not only mention his diſtinction, but takes pains to argue it of in Page 27 and 28. of my Book, and yet this man hath the confidence to tell his Reader in Page 2. of his Book, <hi>that I left it out, and relate only his denial of the Major.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, A third omiſſion he chargeth me with is that in my Book, <hi>I left all the explication</hi> (he gave) <hi>of inlightning which he infered from</hi> 1 John 5. Luke 4.1. <hi>how that all inlightning was not a Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:37391:15"/>of true believers unleſs the Devil, be a true believer;</hi> See his Book Page 10. Now that this is a notorious falſity any one may ſee, that reads my Book, Page 46. 47. in which Pages I bring in Mr. <hi>Danſon,</hi> thus anſwering upon this diſtinction. <hi>A perſon</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>may be ſo far inlightned (and not a true believer) as to aſſent to this propoſition that Jeſus Chriſt is the Son of God,</hi> 1 John 5. <hi>compared with</hi> Luke 4 4. <hi>here are both the Texts that he grounds the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinction, and the explication it ſelf,</hi> and then in Page 47. I bring him in giving a further explica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of himſelf in theſe words, <hi>I have ſhewen you</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>that peſons may be ſo far inlight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, as to believe that Jeſus is the Chriſt, as the Devils themſelves did, yet</hi> (he ſaith Page 10.) <hi>all this explication of inlightning I have omitted,</hi> if men can ſpeak falſely at ſuch a wilful rate, they deſerve not to be credited when they ſpeak the truth.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, He ſaith I omitted his Argument of the 1. <hi>John</hi> 3.9. <hi>Whoſoever is born of God cannot ſin,</hi> &amp;c. ſee his Book P. 47. Now ſee my Book Page 101, 102, 103. where I bring in Mr. <hi>Danſon,</hi> not only quoting the Text, but in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferring from it ſeveral times that believers can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not ſin as wicked men do, as a y may ſee that reads my book, where I expreſs and r<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>peat his Arguments with all his improvements of it, and yet this man ſaith ſaith I have omited it.</p>
            <p>Fif<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hly, He ſaith <hi>my diſingenuity is remark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, that I leave out the word Spiritual, which
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:37391:16"/>(ſaith he) I did often, perhaps not always add as a limitation of the promiſes made to</hi> Iſrael; See his book p. 56.</p>
            <p>Here Mr. <hi>Danſon</hi> chargeth me with an <hi>Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phaſis,</hi> not onely for being <hi>diſingenious,</hi> but adds, that I am <hi>remarkably diſingenious for leaving out the word Spiritual,</hi> in his argument on <hi>Jer.</hi> 32. But Mr. <hi>Danſon</hi> is the more re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>markably diſhoneſt for falc<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>fying my book, and abuſing his Re<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>der, that perhaps may never compare both <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ooks together, for this very word Spiritual I mention ſix times in 5 pages one after another, as ſpoken by Mr. <hi>Danſon</hi> by which he limits the promiſe in the <hi>32d</hi> of <hi>Jer.</hi> as made to <hi>Iſrael</hi> in things ſpiritual; and yet Mr. <hi>Danſon</hi> is ſo carnal as to ſay, <hi>I am re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>markably diſingenious for leaving it out;</hi> for proof hereof, read my book p. 131. where you will find, <hi>I charge him for running in a Ring, and diſputing circularly; and therefore pray him to prove the promiſes in Jer.</hi> 32. <hi>are made to all true believers:</hi> then I bring in Mr. <hi>Danſon,</hi> giving this anſwer, IN SPIRITUAL THINGS ſaith he, here I mention the word the firſt time, again, I mention it the ſecond time in page 132. where I charge him with ſaying, <hi>whatever is predicated of all the Iſrael of God, is predicated of all true believers;</hi> to this I bring in Mr. <hi>Danſon</hi> giving this anſwer, <hi>I told you</hi> (ſaith he) IN SPIRITUAL THINGS. The third time I mention it, is in p. 132. <hi>That
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:37391:16"/>there may be ſome promiſes made to the Iſrael of God, that are not appropriated to all true beleiv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers;</hi> I bring Mr. <hi>Danſon</hi> in uſing this limitati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, <hi>I ſay</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>as to SPIRIT<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>AL ble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings;</hi> I mention him uſing the ſame phraſe a fourth time in the ſame forecited p. 133. this clauſe (ſaith he) <hi>I will put my fear in their hearts,</hi> IS SPIRITUAL, <hi>my argument</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>lies in that;</hi> the fifth time I mention the word, is in p. 134. of my book, there I bring in Mr. <hi>Danſon</hi> ſpeaking thus, <hi>I bring this Text</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>to prove that the phraſe the Iſrael of God, comprehends all true believers; becauſe</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>that the promiſe that is here made is SPIRIT<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>AL.</hi> A 6th. time I mention the word, is in p. 135. of my book, where I tell him, <hi>he is to conclude that all the promiſes that are made to the Iſrael of God, are made to all true believers:</hi> To this I bring in Mr. <hi>Danſon,</hi> giving this an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, <hi>I ſay</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>it is the promiſe in</hi> SPI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>RITUAL <hi>things.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I have put this word <hi>Spiritual</hi> in Capitals, that all may ſee he is as capitally Criminal in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>praving my Writings, both in the words, and very letter of them, as he is in defaming my perſon; for every paſſage that threatens dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger to his cauſe muſt be mutilated and diſmem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred; and as <hi>Sampſon</hi> was by the <hi>Philiſtines,</hi> loſe its hair and eyes, and then (as one well ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerves upon the ſame occaſion) be made ſport for the whole party.</p>
            <p n="6">
               <hi>6ly</hi> Mr. <hi>Danſon</hi> accuſeth me in p. 49. of his book for ſaying, <hi>that the promiſe of the Land of</hi> Canaan <hi>had
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:37391:17"/>no condition expreſsed or implied in all the Scripture,</hi> which is notoriouſly falſe; for it was onely a ſtranger that was at <hi>the</hi> Diſpute, that did accuſe me for ſaying ſo, but I preſently convinced him of his miſtake: for which he publickly craved my pardon, as I relate it in my book, 122. and which is not denied by Mr. <hi>Danſon;</hi> and yet he mounts upon confidence, and ſays I ſaid ſo.</p>
            <p n="7">
               <hi>7ly.</hi> Whereas in my Appendix I charge Mr. <hi>Danſon,</hi> and divers other Miniſters; for making one heart with Dr. <hi>Criſp,</hi> by their publiſhing Antinomian notions, that tend to Ranteriſm: Mr. <hi>Danſon</hi> replies, <hi>that how ſmooth<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y ſoever I th nk to ca ry it,</hi> Dr. Criſp <hi>ſpeaks of the Elect; but the other Divines ſpeak of Believers;</hi> See his book, p. 82. But this is as falſe as the reſt; for I ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times bring in Dr. <hi>Criſp,</hi> applying theſe notions to Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lievers, as well as they ſee my book, p. 195. <hi>none</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>dare ſerve a Writ of Damnation on a Believer, though he ſhould b<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> overtaken with groſs ſins;</hi> and ſome of thoſe other Divines, as he calls them, applies the like ſayings to the E ect, as well (it not as ill) as Dr. <hi>Criſp,</hi> for Mr. <hi>Eyres</hi> (whom Dr. <hi>Owen</hi> commends, and whom I quote in my book, p. 196. (ſaith, <hi>that the Elect Corinthians had no more sight to Heaven after they believed, then they had in the midſt of their Fornica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors, Th<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>fts, and Extortions;</hi> And yet this man tells his Reader a ſtory as if it were Dr. <hi>Criſp</hi> that applied theſe ſayings to the Elect; their Miniſters underſtood them of Belieuers.</p>
            <p>There are many more of this kind, which I forbear to name, knowing that theſe inſtances may ſerve ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiently to ſhew all ſo<gap reason="illegible" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> Chriſtians what ſpirit inſpired him in inditeing: his book, wh<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ch though it conſiſts of ſix ſheets of Paper, about 3 of thoſe ſheets are ſpent in creating new Argum<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nts and Anſwers, that he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſ<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>th were not urged in the Diſpute; all which will ſhew that he hath better ski l to anſwer Arguments of his own making then mine: But I ſhall leave the Reader to judge whether Mr. <hi>Danſon</hi> hath ſufficiently anſwered my Arguments, or proved his own, by com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paring the books together.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:37391:17"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
